<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To his Highness the Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74944</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865779</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118030</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240930048</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E863_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206663</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865779</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865779e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E863[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To his Highness the Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "January. 9. 1655".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Textile industry --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118030:1"/>
            <head>To his Highness the Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He humble Representation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters, Contrivers, and Inventers of the Art, Mystery, or Trade of <hi>Frame-worke-knitting,</hi> or making of Silke Stockings, and other Worke in a Frame, or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines; Petitioners to your Highness, that they may be united, and incorporated by Charter under the Great Seale of <hi>England;</hi> Wherby their just Right to the Invention may be preserved from Forreig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the Trade advanced, abuses therein suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, the benefit of the Common-wealth by Importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Exportation, and otherwise increased; and hundreds of poore Families comfortably relieved by their severall imploiments about the same, who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118030:2"/>will otherwise be exposed to ruine, having no other Callings or Trades to live of.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it please your Highness,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AMongst all the civill waies of improvement of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth (next after Agriculture) Merchandise and Manufactury (where, and whensoever orderly regulated) in all ages and times, have been, and are most securely benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and prosperous, during their cherishment and retenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But they are very apt to become volant, as soon as sleighted or disordered into neighbouring<note n="*" place="margin">Many places have had their vicissitude of prosperity and decay, occasioned by accesse and reading of Trade: as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth (amongst many others) <hi>Gaunt</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and those Townes from whence the Engl sh Staple hath removed.</note> places and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, alwaies hospitable to so welcome guests, as bring with them not onely their own entertainments, but also profitable advantages to their Protectors, leaving behind them unto the place of their former residence, an over-late and remedilesse repentance, of such improvidence, and most commonly an irrevocable consumption.</p>
               <p>The experience whereof, hath antiently and generally made it a Principall and Maxime in State, to encourage by all favourable meanes requisite, the Erectors and Practisers of trading; and hath notified for one of the greatest errors in State-government, the discountenancing and disordering thereof.</p>
               <p>Whence in succession of time (from the the antiquity of all Records) have arisen the great variety, and multitude of Incorporations, over-spreading the face of all the eminent parts of the civilly-govern'd World, flourishing under the favour and protection of the severall Princes and States thereof; each Province striving to exceed its Neighbours in numerosity of them, and enlargement of all convenient priviledges, and powers grantable unto them, and reaping innumerable benefits at the cheap rate of countenance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, &amp; protection of the industrious labours of the Natives; who, in retribution unto the State for license and priviledge to earn their own subsistencies, doe disburthen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118030:2"/>the Common-wealth (by emploiment or maintenance) of many poor, keep themselves in closer order, and lesse circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference than others, in ready ability for publike service, pay all publick charges and impositions; draw Commerce into their Country, with profit unto the State, by Importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Exportation, and furnish their own, and all others necessities with usefull commodities. So (and many waies much more) profitable, is encouraged and well govern'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry, which is discouraged, and denyed order, in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, prosecution, and exercise thereof: It sometimes hath, (and ever will) most certainly become a disadvantage, weakning and impoverishment to the Common-wealth, and an advancement, strength, and enrichment of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who are (or may prove) enemies.</p>
               <p>In prevention whereof, all Nations that live not in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute slavery to their Soveraignes, but enjoy a propriety in their Estates and Goods, by claiming also a right of propriety in the fruits of their own endeavours (which was never yet denied, but to the great prejudice of the contradictors) have provided, and do allow,<note place="margin">Many profitable Arts have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished with their Inventors, and many have shifted Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries upon the gripes of State-Officers.</note> that as they severally or successively arrive to any assured profit, they are included within their owne territories, and appropriated unto the particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servers, with Grants in perpetuity of the regulation of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Trade, meerely as matter of power, or the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Ministers thereof, unlesse for justice against infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Invaders of such establishments, as have to that purpose been obtained. And it hath been (and remaineth) a great part of the felicity of England, That by the grave advice and approbation of the State, it aboundeth with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent presidents and provisions of this kind, to the great encouragement and comfort, both of present and future in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustries.</p>
               <p>Whereby the Petitioners are imboldened (now at length) to offer to your Highnesse consideration and grave judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the fulnesse of capacity they humbly conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to have long been in, to receive the like grant of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, trust and protection, which many other Companies
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118030:3"/>have (upon fewer and lesse weighty inducements) obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and whereof there is apparent necessity, their trade be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no longer manageable by them nor secureable unto the profit of this Common-wealth without it.</p>
               <p>Which Trade is properly stiled Frame-worke-knitting, because it is direct and absolute Knit-worke in the stitches thereof; nothing different therein from the common way of Knitting (not much more antiently for publick use, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised in this Nation, than this) but onely in the numbers of needles, at an instant working in this, more than in the other, by an hundred for one, set into an Engine or Frame, composed of above two thousand pieces of Smiths, Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and Turners worke, after so artificiall and exact a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, That (by the Judgement of all beholders) it far excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the ingenuity, curiosity and subtilty of the invention, and contexture, all other Frames or Instruments for Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture in use, in any known part of the world. And for the skill requisite to the use and manage thereof, it well deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth (without usurpation, as some others impertinently have) the titles of Mystery and Art, by reason of the great difficulty of learning, and length of time necessary to attain a dextrous habit of right, true, and exquisite workmanship therein, which hath preserved it hitherto (from the hands of Forreigners) peculiar onely to the English Nation, from whence it had extraction, growth, and breeding, unto that perfection it is now arrived at: Not only able to serve your Highness Dominions with the Commodities it Merchanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly worketh, but also the neighbouring Countries round about, where it hath gained so good repute, that the vent thereof is now more forreign than domestique, and hath drawn covetous eys upon it to undermine it here and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sport it beyond the seas.</p>
               <p>Of whose sinister workings to that pernitious end, these Petitioners (as most interessed) standing in the nearest sent, thinke themselves in the common duty of well affected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to your Highnesse and their Country (besides their own case of necessity) bound to make addresse unto the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118030:3"/>protection, and care of your Highnesse (as their predecessors in former times have done to the Rulers of this Nation) speedily to restraine and suppresse all attempts, to bring so great a detriment, and inconvenience upon this Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Now so it is, may it please your Highnesse,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>That this trade of Frame-worke-knitting, was never known nor practised either here in <hi>England,</hi> on in any other place of the world, before it was (above fifty yeares past) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and found out by one <hi>William Lea</hi> of <hi>Calverton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>William Lea</hi> of <hi>Calverton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Gentleman, the inventor.</note> in the County of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Gentleman; who by himselfe, and such of his Kindred and Country-men, as he took un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for servants, practised the same many yeares, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what imperfectly, in comparison of the exactnesse it is sithence brought unto, by the endeavours of some of these Petitioners. Yet even in the infancy thereof, it gathered sufficient estimation of a businesse of so extraordinary a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall profit and advantage, as to be invited over into <hi>France,</hi> upon allurements of great rewards, priviledge and honour; not long before the sodaine murther of the late French King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, unsuccessefully accepted by the said Mr <hi>Lea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An attempt to carry the Art of Frame worke-knitting to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and set it up there, done, and frustrated.</note> at that time wanting due encouragement at home. And transporting himselfe with nine workmen, his servants (with some Frames) unto <hi>Roan;</hi> there wrought to so great applause of the <hi>French,</hi> that the Trade was in all likelihood, to have been setled in that Country for ever, had not the decease of the said King disappointed Mr <hi>Lea,</hi> of his expected Grant of Priviledge, and the succeeding troubles of that Kingdome, delaid his renewed sute to that purpose, into discontentment and death at <hi>Paris,</hi> leaving his workmen at <hi>Roan</hi> to provide for themselves. Seven of w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> returned back again into <hi>England</hi> (with their Frames) and here practised and improved their Trade: Under whom (or the Master-workmen since risen under them) most of these Petitioners had their breeding, and served their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiships. Of the other two which remained in <hi>France,</hi> onely one is yet surviving: But so far short of the perfection
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118030:4"/>of his Trade (as it is used here) that of him, or what can be done by him, or his meanes, these Petitioners are in no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of feare; nor have not been (since then) endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered in forraign Countries, by any that have served out their full times of Apprentiship here.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An endeavour to set up the said Art in <hi>Venice,</hi> fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated.</note>But neer about that time, a Venetian Embassador gave five hundred pounds for a remnant of time of one <hi>Henry Mead,</hi> then an Apprentice to this Trade, and conveighed him (with his Frame) from <hi>London</hi> unto <hi>Venice,</hi> where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his worke and manner of it was (for a while) admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and endeavoured to be imitated: Yet as soon as necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of reparation of his Frame, and instruments happened, for want of Artificers experienced in such worke there, and of ability in him to direct them, the work prospered not in his managing; so that (his bought time of service being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired) affection to his native Country brought him home againe into <hi>England.</hi> And after his departure, the <hi>Venetians</hi> grew disheartned in the Trade, and impatient of making vain tryals, they sent his disordered Frame (&amp; some of their own imitations) to be sold in <hi>London;</hi> at very low valuations.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An endeavour to set up the said Art in <hi>Holland,</hi> fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated.</note>And within few yeares afterwards, the Trade was greatly endangered by one <hi>Abraham Jones;</hi> who having (by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hand courses and insinuation, and not by service as an Apprentice) gotten both the mystery and skilfull practice thereof, did (contrary to his Articles with the rest of the Company, that had taken some jealous notice of him) passe himselfe with one more unto <hi>Amsterdam;</hi> and there (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king some Dutch unto him as servants) erected Frames, and wrought for the space of two or three yeares, untill the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the plague seized on him and his whole family, and carried them all to the grave. His Frames also (as things unprofitable to them that could not finde out their right use, without an able teacher) were sent to <hi>London</hi> for sale at slight rates.</p>
               <p>These preservations and escapes of this Trade from trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation into forreign Countries, these Petitioners doe with thankfulnesse acknowledge, and ascribe to have been
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118030:4"/>brought to passe by the divine providence, limiting his bounties and administrations whither he hath been pleased to direct them. For it may well seem marvellous in humane judgements, how otherwise this Trade should remain (notwithstanding all the covetous and envious attempts to the contrary, practised both at home and abroad, for the space of forty yeares past) an Art peculiar onely to this our Nation: And to the nimble spirits of the French; the fertile wits of the Italians, and the industrious inclinations of the Dutch, a concealed mystery unto this day.</p>
               <p>Yet a continued negligence in presumption thereupon, would ill beseem the receivers of so many dammageles war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and may soon prove of hard consequence unto these Petitioners, who are without intermission, environed with the like or greater dangers.<note place="margin">The intruders abuses.</note> For there are by other meanes than the way of Apprentiship, so many intruders crept into this Trade, that ill worke and ill ware is every where of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to sale; and the ignominy and disparagement thereof, commonly imputed to the whole Manufacture, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much losse, hinderance, and interruption to the true and allowable Artizans, and tending to their utter impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishment, who (in continuall workmanship) produce the best, finest, and most approvedly Merchandable and usefull ware ever sold or bought in the memory of Man, otherwise the Petitioners could not have driven their Trade (through many oppositions and difficulties) up unto that height it is now brought, and into faire expectation and open way of large increase, if intrusion were barred, and transportation (and teaching of the mystery unto forreigners) restrained; And none of this our Nation (either Artisan, Apprentice or Intruder) be permitted so mischievously to seek for gaine; As one here in <hi>London</hi> maketh his profession and custome to doe;<note place="margin">One maketh it his pr<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssion to teach the art to our own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, for any inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Rates.</note> exposing himselfe a teacher of this Art and Trade, for any inconsiderable parcell of mony, unto all manner of people (without distinction, whether native or not) hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to uncontroleably; nor to inveagle and corrupt Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices from their Masters, to discover and teach unto them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118030:5"/>the whole Trade; and (having gotten it) pretend upon scruple of conscience (in matter of Religion) or some other occasion, to depart your Highnesse Dominions, and set it up in practice in a forreigne Country; as one not long since hath done, whom these Petitioners are labouring all they may to reduce, and are not hopelesse to finde prevalent meanes to recover him backe againe timely enough, if they receive encouragement in this their humble sute. Wherein they further shew,</p>
               <p>That although this Manufacture may be wrought in any other materials that are usually (or can possibly be) made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the forme of Knit-work: yet hath it chosen to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in silk, the best and richest of all other in use and wearing, and most crediting the Artizans, and of greatest advantage unto this State and Commonwealth, yielding several pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the use of the State before it passe out of the hands of the Traders therein,<note place="margin">The benefit to the Common-wealth, by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation and Exportation.</note> and increasing Merchandise by both the waies of Importation and Exportation of the selfe same materiall, imported raw at cheap rates, exported ready wrought at the utmost extent of value; so that the distance of those valuations is totally cleare gaine to this Common-wealth, and esteemed upwards of six parts in seven of the whole quantity of this materiall in the highest value thereof, wrought up by this manufacture; which hath vindicated that old proverbiall aspersion, cast upon this Nation by forreig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>The stranger buyeth of the English man, the case of a Fox for a Groat,</hi>
                  <note> PLACE="marg" An Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                  <hi>and selleth him the taile againe for a Shilling;</hi> And may now invert and retort on them: <hi>The English man buyeth Silke of the stranger for twenty Marks, and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him the same again for an hundred pounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That this Trade encourageth and setteth on work other Artificers also; as Smiths Joyners, and Turners, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, erecting, and repairing of the Frames, and other neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary instruments thereunto belonging: and hath bred up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent workemen among them for further publick service.</p>
               <p>That the Artizans of this Trade, doe moreover imploy a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118030:5"/>multitude of hands (besides their owne) about the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and finishing of the materiall,<note place="margin">Many imploid.</note> and ware they work: On which doe competently subsist and thrive; The Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Throwesters, Sizers, Seamers, and Trimmers thereof: and also their Needle-makers totally depend thereon.</p>
               <p>That although these Petitioners seeme in the eies of the world, to be (at present) under a cloud, and every moment ready to be undone by intruders and forreigners;<note place="margin">The prejudice by abuses of Intruders and want of order.</note> so that many people fear, and forbeare to bind their children Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices unto a trade of such instant hazard and irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, untill a settlement thereof, under a Corporation, to the great retarding an increase of able Artizans; who are therefore but few, in comparison of the number of Knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the way common to other Nations; yet doe they sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist by their labours, in a more substantiall and serviceable degree in the Common-wealth, disburthening it of many poore of both sexes: Whereas that common tedious way multiplyeth needy persons here, rather because the people of other Nations, outworke those of this therein, then by any hinderance they receive from the best Artisans of this Manufacture, that bend their endeavours (all they can) to the forreign vent, in generall (as well as in their own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars) most profitable to this Nation, leaving the home-sale (in great part) unto the common Knitters, uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, unlesse by the intruders into this Art, whose multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation (if not restrained) will be equally as pernicious and destructive unto them, as unto these Petitioners; who onely (and not the common Knitters) have shewed unto this Common-wealth, that it is able abundantly to serve it selfe, <hi>&amp; ultra,</hi> with all commodities of Knit-worker, as Stoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Calceoons, Wastecoats, and many other things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help (or rather inconvenience) it formerly had of importation of the same in quantity, ready wrought from forreign parts. That this Trade is in no kind impertinent or dammageable to the Common-wealth, nor driven in trifling, base or unnecessary stuff &amp; ware (seeing al the world, where habits are worne, is in generall and permanent use thereof)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118030:6"/>But to the contrary, it worketh on the principall of stuffs, and maketh commodious and decent ware, for the cover and ornament of the whole body of man, perpetually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable in the fashion; endeavouring (as much as in the Artizans lyeth) to found an inexhaustible Myne within this Nation, already prepared, to become (if it shall please your Highnesse so to establish it) henceforth, the place of sole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort, as to a speciall Mart, of the rich and stable commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wrought by this Manufacture, for the generall service of all the great, honourable and better sorts of Inhabitants, of the whole communicable world.</p>
               <p>That the Petitioners have made a large and competent probation of the worth of this Manufacture in it selfe, and merit thereof to the Common-wealth (for the proportion of its growth) farre exceeding any other that tradeth with forreigners in their own materials, extracting from them (to the use of this Common-wealth,<note place="margin">The great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of this Art.</note> and maintenance of the people of this Land, at forreign charge) upwards of foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score in every hundred, <hi>De claro,</hi> of the whole value now, or that may be hereafter, upon a regular way of trading, dealt in, and defraying out of the other parcell of the hundred (being lesse than twenty currant) all customes, Imposts, and freights, both homewards and outwards; and also reserving the remainder of the twenty, to the manage of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, for as much new unwrought materiall: Which eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in quick passages and returnes of home-trade (by the way twice accounted for unto the Officers of Excise) suddenly and insensibly diffuseth and disperseth it selfe through very many hands, either totally maintaining, or otherwise adding unto the subsistencies of many other severally (in part) before enumerated Trades and Professions, besides this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture the prime wheele, gathering onely thereby, an ordinary ability,<note place="margin">A multitude depending on the Art for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance.</note> to make the rest to move: Viz. Merchants, Owners of Ships, Hosiers, Dyers, Winders, Throwesters, Sizers, Seamers, Trimmers, Wire-drawers, Needle-makers, Smiths, Joyners, Turners, with many other assistants, all having their sufficient contents and inablements to live,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118030:6"/>out of the clear product of the forreign vent, raised and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished by the labours of these Petitioners and their servants; who have voluntarily amongst themselves, kept order in their trading, according to the duty of probationers (hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto) without making any request unto the State, for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular countenance and protection, untill they found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves now risen into a number, not uncapable of an Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration; and their trade into forreign parts, of so great a growing increase (were the momentary dangers of utter ruine, for want of regulating power, diverted) that it may well be esteemed the most improveable way of benefit and advantage of this kinde, apparant to this present age, and (within some late hundreds of yeares past) offered unto this Nation, and presented unto the State (as this now is to your Highnesse) for an inclosure within the boundary of its native soile, where it may receive its proper husbandry.</p>
               <p>That if these Petitioners had no other Inducements to offer, but what every other trade, which is (common also to forreigners) in feare to be over-wrought, and out-sold by them, hath heretofore presented as motives and means to obtaine Charters and Priviledges, and consequent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions by Statute, upon reasons drawn from conveniences accrewing by civill education of some youth of the Land, emploiment of idle persons; serving this Common-wealth with commodities better wrought here, then those trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported hither from beyond the seas, and maintaining many of our people at home, with the same money which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners did get from hence for maintenance of theirs: Yet might the Petitioners (in confidence of the meere right of Subjects) sue for (at least) the like Grant of Priviledge, and power, subordinately (according to the Lawes and consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of this Land) to regulate their owne endeavours in a Company and fraternity among themselves. But these Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners stand not in the same sole capacity that the Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers and others did, at the times of their incorporations: For these have (additionally thereunto) an higher measure of merit towards the Common-wealth, whose interest in all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118030:7"/>the forementioned extraordinary advantages and benefits,<note place="margin">In this Art a higher measure of merit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, then in others formerly Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated.</note> and in the further uses of them, is annexed unto the pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of this Manufacture, and wholly dependant thereon; insomuch, as the Petitioners (in this their humble sute) doe plead unto your Highnesse, a generall cause of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth in grosse, for an inestimable concernment to all posterity, and crave in their own, to be but barely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, as their lawfull endeavours have qualified them, the temporary instruments and servitours to that publick use; which they may reasonably hope shall not now (first of all sorts of men, ever Petitioning semblable favour) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be refused unto them, who have not been wanting to the Common-wealth, in the main service thereof, during its late extremities of danger, but have all been faithfull to their Countrey in every thing, according to their utmost abilities, and have (many of them) undergone much losse of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goods, and perill of life, by and against the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and some of them continue in Military Office unto this day.</p>
               <p>And seeing the Mistress of knowledge (Experience) hath taught, that the sole proprietary of a generally-desired com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, hath a Master-key to command the lock of trading; which whosoever can prudently manage, hath no small ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery over the wealth of the universe. And seeing that this Art of Frame-worke-knitting here in <hi>England</hi> (as Printing formerly in <hi>Germany,</hi> out wrought all the manuall writers of the world) is likewise able to out-worke all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Knitters amongst all Nations, and make the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity (without divulging of the mystery) generally desirable and entertained (as that other was here) with grace and priviledge of importation (by provision of Statute,<note place="margin">More capable of being kept se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, than the Art of Printing</note> 1 <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.) And seeing this is much more capable of secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting then that, by reason of the great difficulty to attain this with long practise, and the facility of the other to be be conceived at first sight. This arising within an entire Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and that other in a region full of divided princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities. This is endued with a quality retentive, to continue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118030:7"/>for many ages, if not ever (although the other could not so in <hi>Germany</hi>) a peculiar in propriety unto this Nation of <hi>England.</hi> Therefore it is fit to be owned as a Native, and (by the hand of your Highnesse) established in that rank, and as the non-pareil of Handy-crafts, to be taken into your pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session inclusively, within your power of command, and speciall protection; who is herein not slightly concerned, because intrusted to husband the Common-wealth, and is the Ballance of Reason, to distinguish between the Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and aims of good and bad Patriots. Some striving to scatter abroad (about all the earth) that harvest, whereof others desire the storing in a Magazine; and some urging the same exploded clamours against the use of engines in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which the file and hammer-workers of a single pin, did heretofore, to divert or retard the priviledging of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Pin-makers, in opposition to those that (now) sue and referre themselves to be considered, according to discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at home; for what they might write their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions every where abroad; if piety to their native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as strongly restrained not them, as they implore the coercive power of your Highnesse to restrain their ill-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, from unravelling the entrals of the Common-wealth, and giving (or yielding) opportunity unto strangers, to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them up, and make that common to all the world, which is (naturally) particular in sole propriety unto this Nation, and prepared for the management of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, in such manner as (in your Highnesse wisedome and great favour) shall be thought expedient for the best advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this Common-wealth, ever in thriving condition, and flourishing by exportation of Commodities, as well arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially as naturally appropriated unto this Island, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to your Highnesse, to have suffered some late de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, in the main supports of its forreign trading, which may receive a great supply and increase, by meanes and good encouragement of this Manufacture, onely in present necessity of the like protection and priviledges that have been granted, confirmed, and are enjoied by many others,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118030:8"/>though of forreign invention and use, and never in possibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of becomming, as this is solely, from hence importable unto all other Nations; all which is humbly submitted to your Highnesse pleasure, with great hopes that you will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously patronize and cherish the honest endeavours of such as aime at the publick good, as well as their own private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And your Petitioners will ever pray, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>